Well, you've come so far and built a really great game and it's almost ready for publishing.
However, one issue we have is the static ness of our game.
Like there are no levels.
With increasing difficulty, our car moves at the same speed.
Our obstacles cars also spawn at the same speed and all this leaves us with a pretty bland game.
So how can we fix this?
How can we make our game more entertaining?
By increasing the difficulty?
Well, we know that one way to increase the difficulty would be by increasing the rate at which obstacle
courses spawn, or even better, by making them move down faster.
So moving to our obstacle course.
Right.
Let's see the two areas that control how fast our obstacle car moves and how fast it spawns into the
game.
Firstly, as you can see, our obstacle car weights 0.6 to 1.2 seconds before it creates a clone and
spawns in.
So this is the one part of code we would need to adjust.
Then looking at this script, you can see that the car constantly changes y.
By minus five.
So this is its movement speed.
And the other part we would also need to adjust.
So now that we have identified the two parts of the code that control the speed and spawn rate of the
sprite, how can we make it that it keeps getting harder as the game progresses?
Well, we could just keep duplicating this code and duplicating it and duplicating it and duplicating
it.
And then, for instance, change this to 0.5 and 1.1 and just keep making the spawn time shorter and
shorter.
But I think you know that that's not the way to go because as you remember, dry code is important.
Meaning don't repeat yourself.
And we're certainly repeating, repeating, repeating ourselves here.
So instead, just like with the other game we created, we can use variables to control our game speed.
But before we go ahead and change, this is important that you understand just how important variables
are in programming.
Now.
Often it's tempting to just enter in a value such as this change y by minus five.
In programming, this is what is called hard coded values.
Now, while this is okay to do, sometimes there are a bunch of disadvantages too.
So let's just take a moment to consider some of them.
Firstly, lack of flexibility.
Imagine you've built a game with ten levels, all with hard coded difficulties.
If you want to change the difficulty rate, like how quickly the game gets difficult, you would have
to adjust each level individually.
Now that's not a very efficient way, right?
Secondly, updates and expansions.
Let's say your game becomes popular and you decide to release an updated version or expansion.
If everything's hard coded, making consistent changes becomes a very tedious task.
Just like with our game, we would need to change the increased speed value for our trees and our road.
And lastly, consistency issues.
One of the main problems you will face is consistency.
Meaning if we have a small change we want to make in our game, we would need to find every value that
is affected by this change.
And if our game is large, this task becomes nearly impossible.
So that all said, we can make our code a lot better by using variables instead of hard coded values
wherever possible.
Then what we can do is have one space where we adjust all the variables, and this way our game is easy
to manage and upgrade.
So moving over to our variables.
Think about what variables we need to create to make our game more adaptable and scalable.
Well, the two things we want to control are our spawn speed and our movement speed.
So let's create this.
So firstly hitting make variable we can call this first one spawn speed.
Hit create.
And once again we can call this next one Movement speed.
And make sure it's a global variable.
By ensuring this button is selected.
So let's do this.
Now firstly, let's change our spawn speed.
Right now it is this hardcoded value of 0.6 and 1.2.
So instead of 0.6, let's drag in the spawn speed variable.
Then, as 0.6 is double the size of 1.2, we can set the second input to spawn speed multiplied by two.
Okay, so right now our cars won't move as our spawn speed is set to zero.
But to test this out, let's quickly set it to 0.6 by simply selecting it here.
Entering in 0.6 and double click.
And as you can see it has changed now hitting play.
There you have it.
I mean, nothing has changed, but it soon will.
So get ready because in the next lesson, we are going to totally upgrade this game and make it truly
adaptable.